Nora England Papers
Nettie Lee Benson Latin American Collection
Nora England Papers
1919-2021
England, Nora C., 1946-2022
2023-17
28.75 linear feet
Benson Latin American Collection, The University of Texas at Austin
Papers of Nora England, a linguistic anthropologist, documents her work on Mayan languages and cultures. The collection contains field notebooks, linguistic fileslips, theses, newsletters, correspondence, teaching materials, books, unpublished work, administrative papers, grant proposals, photographs, and audiovisual materials.
Biographical Sketch
Nora England (1946-2022) was a distinguished linguistic anthropologist well known for both her academic achievements and her activism in support of language documentation, revitalization, and reclamation work among Mayan communities in Guatemala. In 1971, while in graduate school at the University of Florida, she joined the Proyecto Lingüístico Francisco Marroquín (PLFM), a language documentation project in Guatemala that established a research center for Indigenous people to work on their own languages. England’s role was to coordinate research on Mam languages. This work led to her dissertation and well-known book A Grammar of Mam, published in 1983. The work she did with the PLFM set the trajectory for the rest of her career.
In 1990, England co-founded OKMA (Oxlajuuj Keej Maya’ Ajtz’iib’), an Indigenous academy devoted to teaching and research on Mayan languages based in Antigua, Guatemala. OKMA trained many native speakers of Mayan languages in linguistics, including in the documentation of their own languages. The group produced comparative vocabularies, grammars, and literacy manuals in many different Mayan languages.
England held several academic appointments during her career, including Mississippi State University and the University of Iowa, before moving to UT Austin in 2001, where she was a full professor in the Department of Linguistics as well as the first director of the Center for Indigenous Languages of Latin America at the Teresa Lozano Long Institute of Latin American Studies. Shortly thereafter, she founded the Conference on Indigenous Languages of Latin America (CILLA) in 2003. CILLA is significant for two reasons: it was the first linguistics conference held in the U.S. that allowed presentations to be conducted in Spanish and Portuguese, in addition to English, and it has always featured keynotes given by native speakers of a Latin American Indigenous language.
England’s lifelong dedication to the training of Maya People in linguistics and language documentation led to two awards: the MacArthur “genius” grant in 1993 and the Guatemalan Messenger of Peace award in 2019. In recognition of her solidarity with the Mayan people, her friends and collaborators gave her a Mayan name: Ixkeem, “the woman weaver of words,” demonstrating how highly regarded she was within the communities she worked with.
Scope and Contents Note
Research articles and bound publications by others, including theses, newsletters, reports, and PLFM published material, among others. Also includes works by Nora England, articles and papers, conference publications, books, teaching materials, unpublished work, administrative papers and project proposals, field notebooks, materials on grants, fellowships, and funding, in addition to audio visual materials. The collection spans 23 boxes.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored remotely. Advanced notice is required for retrieval.
Please note that certain folders have restrictions, which are detailed in the Box and Folder Inventory
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
England, Nora C., 1946-2022
Subjects (Organizations)
UT Austin (University); Oxlajuuj Keej Maya' Ajtz'iib' (Group); Proyecto Lingüístico Francisco Marroquín
Subjects
Linguistic Anthropology; Indigenous languages--Sources; Mayan languages; Indigenous languages of Latin America; Mam language; Teco language (Mayan)
Places
Antigua (Guatemala); Austin (Tex.); Guatemala
Related Material
Archive of Indigenous Languages of Latin America (AILLA) Collection
Acquisition Information
Donation.
Additions
No further materials are expected for this collection.
Box and Folder Inventory
- Series I: Work by Others
  - Adams, Richard, "Cultural Components of Central America,", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adams, Richard, "Changing Pattterns of Territorial Organization in the Central Highlands of Chiapas, Mexico,", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aissen, Judith, "Lexical Extension and Grammatical Transformations,", 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Aissen, Judith, "Control and Command in Tzotzil Purpose Clauses,", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aissen, Judith, "Surrogate Agreement in Tzotzil,", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aissen, Judith, "Tzotzil Antipassives as One Place Predicates,", 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aissen, Judith, "The Syntax of the Tzotzil Comitative", AAA, 1984 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Allen, Arthur, "Unriddling the Glyphs,", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anderson, Stephen, "On the Notion of Subject in Ergative Languages,", undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annis, Sheldon, "A Story From a Peaceful Town,", 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ayres, Glenn, "Gramatica de la Lengua Ixil,", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ayres, Glenn, "Es el Antipasivo Siempre una Voz?,", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bendor-Samuel, John, "Niger-Congo, Gur,", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bergeron, Leandre, "Dictionnaire de la Langue Quebecoise,", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Berlin, Brent, "Categories of Eating in Tzeltal and Navaho,", 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Berlin, Brent, "A Possible Pragmatic Structure for Tzeltal Pronominals,", undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Berthelot, Jacques, "Approche Syntaxique du Maya-Tzutuhil (Guatemala),", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bloomfield, Leonard, "Outline Guide for the Practical Study of Foreign Languages,", 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Blount, Ben, "Extra-Linguistic Features in Bilingualism,", undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bourque, Susan and Kay B. Warren, "Democracy without Peace: The Politics of Terror in Peru,", 1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brice Heath, Shirley, "Language and (as) Culture? Old Questions in New Times", American Anthropological Association, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bricker, Victoria, "Pronominal Inflection in the Mayan Languages,", undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bricker, Victoria, "Antipassive Construction in Yucatec Maya,", undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bricker, Victoria and George Collier, "Nicknames and Social Structure in Zinacantan,", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bricker, Victoria, "Three Genres of Tzotzil Insult,", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bricker, Victoria, "Some Cognitive Implications of Informant Variability in Zinacanteco Speech Classification,", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bricker, Victoria, "Relationship Terms with the Usative Suffix in Tzotzil and Yucatec Maya,", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Briggs, Charles, "Linguistic Ideologies and the Naturalization of Power in Warao Discourse,", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Briggs, Charles, "On Death and Identity: Etiology and the Spatialization of Discourse in Narrative Explanations of a South American Cholera Epidemic,", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Briggs, Lucy, "Aymara Morphology,", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Briggs, Lucy, "Linguistics and Foreign Aid,", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Briggs, Lucy, "Missionary, Patron, and Radio Aymara", American Anthropological Association, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Briggs, Lucy, "Bilingual Education in Bolivia,", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bright, William, "Literature: Written and Oral,", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Brintnall, Douglas, "Race Relations in the Southeastern Highlands of Mesoamerica,", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Brody, Jill, "To Have and to Hold - Gapping in Tojolabal-Mayan", American Anthropological Association, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Brody, Jill, "Cleft in Tojolabal Maya: Structure and Discourse Function,", undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Brody, Jill, "Repetition as a Rhetorical and Conversational Device in Tojolabal (Mayan),", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Brody, Jill, "Some Problems with the Concept of Basic Word Order,", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Brody, Jill, "Discourse Genres in Tojolabal,", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Brody, Jill, "Discourse Processes of Highlighting in Tojolabal Maya Morphosyntax,", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Brody, Jill, "Cleft in Tojolabal Maya", American Anthropological Association, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Brody, Jill, Proposal, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Brown, Cecil H., "Proto-Mayan Syllable Nuclei,", 2000 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Brown, Cecil H., Various Articles, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Brown, Cecil H., "Where do Cardinal Direction Terms Come From?,", 1983 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Brown, Cecil H., "Folk Anatomy and Language Change,", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Brown, Cecil H., "More on Folk Zoological Life-Forms,", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Brown, Cecil H., "Growth and Development of Folk Botanical Life Forms in the Mayan Language Family,", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Brown, Cecil H., "Folk Botanical Life-Forms,", June 1977 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Brown, Cecil H. and Stanley H. Witkowski, "Aspects of the Phonological History of Mayan-Zoquean,", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Brown, Penelope, "Women are More Polite,", undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Camposeco, Jeronimo, "El Pueblo de los Indios: Indiantown, Florida", Latin American Studies Association, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Cancian, Frank, "State and Church Effects on Community Boundaries of Zinacantan,", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Canger, Una, "Report on Tne::L U7J,", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Can Pixabaj, Telma, "La Topicalización en K'ichee': Una Perspectiva Discursiva,", 2004 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Cardenas, Rene and Charlotte Miller, "Federal Research Direction in Bilingual Education", Southern Anthropological Society, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Chafe, Wallace, "Givenness, Contrastiveness, Definiteness, Subjectts, Topics, and Point of View,", undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Chafe, Wallace and Deborah Tannen, "The Relation Between Written and Spoken Language,", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Cohen, Andrew, "Researching Bilingualism in the Classroom,", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Cojti Cuxil, Demetrio, "Problemas de la Identidad Nacional Guatemalteca,", undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Cojti Macario, Narciso, "Informe General,", undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Cojti Macario, Narciso and Martín Chacach Cutzal, "La Aplicacion de la Linguistica en el Desarollo de una Comunidad Indigena", American Anthropological Association, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Cojti Macario, Narciso and Martín Chacach Cutzal, "Curso Cakchiquel: Gramatica Estructural,", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Collins, Jane, "Translation Traditions and the Organization of Productive Activity: The Case of Aymara Affinal Kinship Terms,", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Collins, Wes, "Long Vowels in Certain Phonological Phrases in Mam,", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Conklin, Harold, "Hanunoo Color Categories,", 1955 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Craig, Colette, "Jacaltec Noun Classifiers: A Study in Language and Culture,", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Craig, Colette, "Jacaltec Noun Classifiers: A Study in Grammaticalization,", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Craig, Colette, "The Antipassive and Jacaltec,", undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Craig, Colette, "A Grammar of Rama,", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Craig, Colette, "Agentivity in Jacaltec (Mayan),", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Craig, Colette, "On the Promotion of Instrumentals in Tzutujil and Jacaltec", American Anthropological Association, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Craig, Colette, "Agentes en Jacalteco,", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Craig, Colette, "Properties of Basic and Derived Subjects in Jacaltec,", undated (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Croft, William, "Transitivity and Possession in Quiche (and elsewhere),", undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Croft, William, "Cross-reference, Ergativity and Categoriality in Quiche,", undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Dakin, Karen, "Verb Phrases as Morphological Bases in Kanjobal and Acatec,", 1974 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Dakin, Karen, "Plural Formations in Morelos Nahuate", American Anthropological Association, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Dakin, Karen, "Complex Sentences in Amilcingo (Morelos) Nahuatl,", 1974 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Davies, William and Enrique Sam-Colop, "Regularizing K'iche' Verb Agreement,", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Davies, William and Enrique Sam-Colop, "K'iche' and the Structure of Antipassive,", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - DeCicco, Gabriel and Joel Maring, "Diglossia, Regionalism, and National Language Policy: A comparison of Spain and the Philippines,", undated (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - DeCormier, Christopher, "Kekchi Particle čaq: Relations in Time and Space,", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Du Bois, John, "Self-Evidence and Ritual Speech,", 1983 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Du Bois, John, "Competing Motivations,", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Du Bois, John, "Some Problems in Mayan Classification and Comparison,", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Du Bois, John, "Ergativity and Preferred Argument Structure in Sacapultec Discourse,", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Du Bois, John, "Discourse Equilibrium and Stable Ergativity: A Mayan Case,", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Du Bois, John, "Absolutive Zero,", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Durbin, Marshall and Fernando Ojeda, "Basic Word Order in Yucatec Maya,", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Edmonson, Barbara, "How to Become Bewitched, Bothered, and Bewildered: The Huastec Inchoative,", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Edmonson, Barbara, "The Huastec Applicative", handout, undated (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Epps, Patience, "Hup's Typological Treasures: Description and Explanation in the Study of an Amazonian Language,", 2008 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Esposito, Christina Marie, "Santa Ana Del Valle Zapotec Phonation", MA thesis, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Farber, Anne, "Sex Antagonism in Two Cakchiquel Myths", American Anthropological Association presentation, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Farber, Anne, "Language Choice and Sex Roles in Highland Guatemala", American Anthropological Association meeting, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Farber, Anne, "Social Constraints on Bilingual Usage", research proposal, 1972 December (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Fischer, Edward F., "The West in the Future: Cultural Hegemony and the Politics of Identity,", 1993 December (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fischer, Edward F., "Yaqui Voices and Spanish Texts, or Inquiries into Yaqui History,", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fischer, Edward F., "Mayan Revitalization and the Politics of Culture and Development in Two Kaqchikel Towns", dissertation and CV, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fischer, Edward F. and Jankowiak, William R., "A Cross-Cultural Perspective on Romantic Love,", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fishman, Joshua A., "Language and Nationalism: Two Integrative Essays,", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Foley, William A. and Olson, Mike, "Clausehood and Verb Serialization,", undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Foster, George M., "Speech Forms and Perception of Social Distance in a Spanish-Speaking Mexican Village,", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Friedman, Lynn A., "The Manifestation of Subject, Object, and Topic in the American Sign Language,", undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Friedrich, Paul, "On the Meaning of the Tarascan Suffixes of Space,", 1969 October (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Friedrich, Paul, "Poetic Language and the Imagination,", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Froman, Jo, Bob Gersony, and Tony Jackson, "A History of the Proyecto Lingüístico Francisco Marroquín,", 1978 December (Box 21)
  - Furbee, N. Louanna, "Identity in Gapping and the Lexical Insertion of Words,", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Furbee, N. Louanna, "Cognitive and Geographic Maps: Study of Individual Variation Among Tojolabal Mayans,", 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Furbee, N. Louanna, "To Ask One Holy Thing: Petition as a Tojolabal Maya Speech Genre,", undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Furbee, N. Louanna, "Ancient and Modern Maya Spiked Vessels,", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Furbee, N. Louanna, "Report to NEH on Text and Dictionary Project,", 1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Furbee, N. Louanna, "A Position Paper for Participants in the Language in Anthropology Symposium", American Anthropological Association Annual Meeting, 1985 December-1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Furbee, N. Louanna, "Tojolabal (Mayan) Kinterms and the Theory of Markedness, or a Near Triumph of the Feminine Gender,", undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Furbee, N. Louanna, Robert A. Benfer, and Raquel Vega, "Acerca de la Relacion Entre Modelos Linguisticos y Anthropologos,", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Furbee, N. Louanna and Martha J. Macri, "Mayan High Ejective Consonants,", undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Garcia-Ruiz, Jesús F., "El Defensor y El Defendidi: Dialectica de la Agresion Entre los Mochó (Motozintla, Chiapas),", 1982 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Garzón, Susan, "Basic Word Order" in Teco, 1985 January (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Garzón, Susan, "The Process of Language Death in a Mayan Community in Southern Mexico,", 1986 August 19 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Garzón, Susan, "Language Death in a Mayan Community in Southern Chiapas,", 1985 May (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Garzón, Susan, "Some Recommendations for Teaching Kaqchikel Grammar to Students in Urban Schools,", 1989 September 7 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Gates, William E., "Materials Related to Gates' Collecting Activities,", undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Godenzzi, Juan Carlos, "Lenguas, Discursos e Identidades en el Sur Andino Peruano,", 1996 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Graham, Laura, "A Public Sphere in Amazonia? The Depersonalized Collaborative Construction of Discourse in Xavante,", 1993 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Graham, Laura, "How Should an Indian Speak? Amazonian Indians and the Sympolic Politics of Language in the Global Public Sphere,", undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Graham, Laura, "Discourse-Centered Methods,", 1998 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Graham, Laura, "The One Who Created the Sea,", 2000 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Graham, Laura, "Lessons in Collaboration: The Xavante/WFF Wildlife Management Project in Central Brazil,", 2000 February (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Graham, Laura, "Authentic or Counterfeit? Language and Symbolic Politics of Amazonian Indians in the Global Public Sphere,", 1996 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Greenberg, Joseph H., "Numeral Classifiers and Substantival Number: Problems in the Genesis of a Linguist,", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Greenberg, Joseph H., "A Quantitative Approach to the Morphological Typology of Language,", undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Greenberg, Joseph H., "Some Universals of Grammar with Particular Reference to the Order of Meaningful Elements,", undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Greenway, Christine, "Religious Innovation and Ethnic Identity in a Quechua Community,", undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Gudschinsky, Sarah C., "The ABC's of Lexicostatistics (Glottochronology),", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Hale, Charles, "Autonomy and Practical Politics in Southeastern Nicaragua,", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Hale, Kenneth, papers on bilingualism, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Hale, Kenneth, "On the Use of Informants in Field-Work,", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Hale, Kenneth, "Misumalpan Verb Sequencing Constructions,", undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Hale, Kenneth, Aviles, A., and Salamanca, D., "Insubordinate Complements in Miskito,", undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Hardman, Martha J., "Jaqara Color Terms,", undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Hardman, Martha J., "The Imperial Languages of the Andes" and "Gentiles in Jaqi Folktales, an Example of Contact Literature,", Winter 1984 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Hardman, Martha J., "Linguistic Postulates and Applied Anthropological Linguistics,", undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Hardman, Martha J., anthropology programs, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Haviland, John, "That's not MY language: Land Rights and Language in Southeastern Cape York Peninsula,", undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Heath, Jeffrey, "Is Dyirbal Ergative?,", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Hill, Jane, "Today There Is No Respect: Nostalgia, "Respect" and Oppositional Discourse in Mexicano (Nahuatl) Language Ideology,", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Hock, Hans Henrich, "Sanskrit as a Spoken Language: Dead, Dying, or Still Alive?,", undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Hock, Hans Henrich, "Proto-Indo-European Reconstruction and Syntactic Typology: A Different Approach,", 1992 February 2 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Hofling, Charles A., various articles, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Hopkins, Nicholas A., "Numeral Classifiers in Tzeltal, Jacaltec, and Chuj (Mayan)", paper presented to the Mayan Linguistics Symposium, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Hopkins, Nicholas A., "Compound Place Names in Chuj and Other Mayan Languages,", 1969 August (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Hopkins, Nicholas A. and J. Kathryn Josserand, "Pasado, Presente y Futuro en la Linguistica Maya,", undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Hopper, Paul J. and Thompson, Sandra A., "Transitivity in Grammar and Discourse,", 1980 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Hymes, Dell, "Discovering Oral Performance and Measured Verse in American Indian Narrative,", 1977 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Irvine, Judith, "Language Ideology and Linguistic Differentiation,", 1996 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Ixim, Inc., "El Vocero de Ixim,", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Jackson, Jean, "Contrasting Discourses in Colombian National Indigenous Politics: The Occupation of the Summer of 1996," (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Jakobson, Roman and Morris Halle, "Fundamentals of Language,", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Jelinek, Eloise and Fernando Escalante, "Passives, Impersonals, and Middles in Yaqui,", 1987 November (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Josserand, J. Kathryn, Linda Schele, and Nicholas A. Hopkins, "Linguistic Data on Maya Inscriptions: the Ti Constructions,", 1980 September (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Josserand, J. Kathryn, "The Narrative Structure of Hieroglyphic Texts at Palengue,", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Julca Guerrero, Felix, various publications, circa 2000s (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, "Comparative Mayan Verb Morphology,", undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, "Mayan Vocabulary Survey,", undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, "Archaeological and Linguistic Correlations in Mayaland and Associated Areas of Meso-America,", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, "Orthographic Principles for Writing Mayan Languages (and Other Indigenous Languages of Spanish-Speaking Latin America),", circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, The Long List, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, Copy of the Long List, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, Fragment of Mayan Vocabulary Survey, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, Etymologies I, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, Etymologies II, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, "Orthographic Principles of Writing Mayan Languages (and other Indigenous Languages of Latin America),", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, "Outline of Comparative Mayan Grammar,", 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, "Linguistic Classification in South America,", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Kaufman, Terrence, Notes, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Kephart, Ronald, "Bilingual Aspects of Language in a Creole Community,", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Knowles, Susan M., "Pronominal Inflection in Chontal Maya (San Carlos Dialect)", handout for American Anthropological Association meeting, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Knowles-Berry, Susan M., "Negation in Chontal Mayan", rough draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Koizumi, Junji, "On the Mam Notion of "Sin": An Exercise in Cultural Analysis", presented at American Anthropological Association meeting, 1979 December 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)